National Visionary Leadership Project Interviews and Conference Collection AFC 2004/007
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series III: Interviews
  - Earl Caldwell oral history interview conducted by Tiffany Shepard, 2006-06-26, AFC 2004/007: 140
    The interview includes Earl Caldwell's memories of growing up in Pennsylvania and his early career at local newspapers. He recalls covering the civil rights movement for the New York Times and being the only reporter at the scene when Martin Luther King, Jr. was assassinated. He also discusses reporting on the Black Panther Party and the resulting Supreme Court case United States v. Caldwell, which set precedent for reporters' rights.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655455
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (47 pages) (Box-folder 14/162)
    - Graphic Images, 5 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/452)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 140.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 140.MV.002
  - James "Winky" Camphor oral history interview conducted by Adam Grant, 2004, AFC 2004/007: 141
    James Winky Camphor was a teacher who worked with boys in the juvenile justice system.
    The interview includes James Camphor's memories of growing up in Maryland and attending Coppin State University. He recalls the segregation in Maryland, becoming a teacher and working with boys in the Cheltenham Juvenile Justice Facility. He also discusses his faith and his opinions on politics.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655578
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (14 pages) (Box-folder 14/163)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 141.MV.001
  - Ernestine Carreathers oral history interview conducted by Tiffany Balkaran, 2003, AFC 2004/007: 142
    Ernestine Carreathers was a teacher and bookstore owner.
    The interview includes Ernestine Carreathers' memories of growing up in Texas and attending Wiley College and Southeastern Oklahoma State University. She recalls meeting her husband, having children and opening a bookstore for African American writers in Prairie View, Texas. She discusses her teaching career, school desegregation, the civil rights movement and her involvement at church.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655579
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (90 pages) (Box-folder 14/164)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (MiniDV) (180 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 142.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 142.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 142.MV.003
  - Julia Carson oral history interview conducted by Brittany Baird, 2005-11-05, AFC 2004/007: 143
    Julia Carson was a member of the Indiana House of Representatives and the U.S. House of Representatives.
    The interview includes Julia Carson's memories of her childhood, her mentor Andy Jacobs and her election to the Indiana House of Representatives. She recalls her efforts to pass minimum wage laws, end the legal classification of children as "illegitmate," and serving as a trustee for the Center Township, a welfare agency, and assisting victims of domestic violence. She also discusses her work as a U.S. Representative, her advocacy of women's rights and civil rights, and her health problems.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655580
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (31 pages) (Box-folder 14/165)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 143.MV.001
  - Robert Churchwell oral history interview conducted by Jerrard A. Davis, 2002-10-30, AFC 2004/007: 144
    Robert Churchwell was a journalist and the first African American reporter for the Nashville Banner.
    The interview includes Robert Churchwell's memories of growing up in Tennessee, serving in the army during World War II, and attending Fisk University. He recalls meeting his wife, starting his own magazine and being recruited by the Nashville Banner to cover the local African American community. He discusses facing discrimination at the newspaper, covering school desegregation and the civil rights movement and his struggle with depression.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655558
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (35 pages) (Box-folder 15/166)
    - Graphic Images, 3 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/453)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (Mini DV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (Mini DV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 144.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 144b.MV.001
  - Mildred Clarke oral history interview conducted by Rita Nicholson-Weaver, 2005, AFC 2004/007: 145
    Mildred Clarke was a doctor specializing in gynecology and obstetrics.
    The interview includes Mildred Clarke's memoires of growing up in Brooklyn, New York, attending Hunter College and Howard University Medical School. She recalls interning at several hospitals for her training in gynecology and obstetrics and her memories of the civil rights movement and John F. Kennedy's assassination. She also discusses her volunteer work with several Christian organizations and her involvement at Calvert Baptist Church.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655581
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (11 pages) (Box-folder 15/167)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 145.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 145.MV.002
  - Margaret Washington Clifford oral history interview conducted by Anna Steed, 2004-10-16, AFC 2004/007: 146
    Margaret Washington Clifford was a teacher, principal and the granddaughter of Booker T. Washington.
    The interview includes Margaret Washington Clifford's memories of growing up in Tuskegee, Alabama, attending the Tuskegee Institute and marrying her husband, a Tuskegee Airman. She recalls moving to California, teaching at a junior high and becoming a guidance counselor and vice principal. She discusses her teaching methods, the influence of her grandfather, Booker T. Washington, and her candy business.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655582
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (32 pages) (Box-folder 15/168)
    - Graphic Images, 1 photograph: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/454)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 146.MV.001
  - Clinton McCord oral history interview conducted by Courtney Norman, 2006, AFC 2004/007: 147
    Clinton McCord played baseball for several Negro League and Minor League teams.
    The interview includes Clinton McCord's memories of growing up in Nashville, Tennessee, playing baseball, and serving in the navy during World War II. He recalls attending Tennessee State University and playing baseball in the Negro Leagues for the Nashville Cubs and Baltimore Elite Giants. He discusses playing for several integrated minor league teams, the influence of baseball on the civil rights movement and the racism that still exists in sports.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655279
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (65 pages) (Box-folder 15/169)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 147.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 147.MV.002
  - Eugenia Collier oral history interview conducted by Zia Holder, 2006-10-06, AFC 2004/007: 148
    Eugenia Collier was a writer, poet and professor of English.
    The interview includes Eugenia Collier's memories of growing up in Baltimore, Maryland and attending Howard University and Columbia University. She recalls raising her family while still a student, working for the Department of Public Welfare, writing her short story "Marigolds" and earning her Ph.D. She discusses the history of African American literature, teaching at several universities and her advice to young African Americans.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655583
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (42 pages) (Box-folder 15/170)
    - Graphic Images, 14 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/455)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 148.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 148.MV.002
  - Frances Cress Welsing oral history interview conducted by Nailah Banks, 2005, AFC 2004/007: 149
    Frances Cress Welsing was a psychiatrist and racial theorist.
    The interview includes Frances Cress Welsing's memories of growing up in Chicago, Illinois and attending Antioch College and Howard Medical School. She recalls her career as a psychiatrist, being denied tenure because of her racial theories, and meeting Malcolm X. She discusses her theories of white supremacy, racism, and white genetic annihilation.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655584
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (30 pages) (Box-folder 15/171)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 149.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 149.MV.002
  - Flora Crittenden oral history interview conducted by Chikara Kennedy, 2002, AFC 2004/007: 150
    Flora Crittenden was a teacher and member of the Virginia House of Delegates.
    The interview includes Flora Crittenden's memories of growing up in Brooklyn, New York and Newport News, Virginia and attending Virginia State College. She recalls teaching high school in Virginia, her teaching philosophy and school integration. She discusses working for Congressman Bobby Scott, her election to the Newport News City Council and the Virginia House of Delegates.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655585
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (34 pages) (Box-folder 15/172)
    - Graphic Images, 2 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/456)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 150.MV.001
  - Wendell Davis oral history interview conducted by Donna Pittman, 2003-01-06, AFC 2004/007: 151
    Wendell Davis was a principal, professor, coach and Texas state education administrator.
    The interview includes Wendell Davis' memories of growing up in Texas, attending Prairie View A & M University and serving in the air force during the Korean War. He recalls his career as an elementary school principal, becoming a professor and coach at Prairie View and guiding the golf team to several championships. He also discusses his career with the Texas Education Agency and raising his family.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655587
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (32 pages) (Box-folder 15/173)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (DVC) (64 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 151.MV.001
  - Gerald Deas oral history interview conducted by Garrett Webster, 2004, AFC 2004/007: 152
    Gerald Deas was a physician, health activist and writer.
    The interview includes Gerald Deas' memories of growing up in Brooklyn, New York, racist images in popular culture, serving in the army during the Korean War and attending medical school. He recalls his career as a family doctor in Queens, New York, making house calls and his service to the community. He also discusses his church involvement, writing poetry and his radio show, "House Call."
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655588
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (93 pages) (Box-folder 15/174)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 152.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 152.MV.002
  - Georgia Dickens oral history interview conducted by Daria Grayer, 2002-12-11, AFC 2004/007: 153
    Georgia Dickens was a teacher and civic leader.
    The interview includes Georgia Dickens' memories of growing up in Atlanta, Georgia and attending Spelman College. She recalls her elementary school teaching career, serving on the boards of the Children's Theatre Guild and the High Museum of Art. She also discusses her faith, her relationships with her students and the importance of volunteering.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655589
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (35 pages) (Box-folder 15/175)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 153.MV.001
  - Betty Jean Dobson oral history interview conducted by Kenneth Pardovani, 2004, AFC 2004/007: 154
    Betty Jean Dobson was the communications director of the Harlem Hospital.
    The interview includes Betty Jean Dobson's memories of growing up in Ohio, working as a beautician and attending Queens College and Fordham University for her master's degree. She recalls her career as the communications director of Harlem Hospital, promoting public health in New York and her firing over sexual harassment. She also discusses her memories of the civil rights movement and founding the organization Committee to Eliminate Media Offensive to African People.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2011655249
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (49 pages) (Box-folder 15/176)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 154.MV.001
  - Shirley Douglas oral history interview conducted by Josephine Steadman, 2005, AFC 2004/007: 155
    Shirley Douglas was a Department of Labor employee.
    The interview includes Shirley Douglas' memories of growing up in Washington, D.C. and Virginia, and facing segregation on public transportation. She recalls her career at the Department of Labor and racial discrimination in the workplace. She discusses her family, involvement at church and her opinions on the care of seniors.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655590
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (32 pages) (Box-folder 15/177)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 155.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 155.MV.002
  - Elizabeth Edmonds oral history interview conducted by Dara Foster, 2005, AFC 2004/007: 156
    Elizabeth Edmonds was a teacher, principal and professor.
    The interview includes Elizabeth Edmonds' memories of growing up in Baltimore, Maryland, her first jobs and attending Loyola College. She recalls facing discrimination at her first teaching position, her career as a principal who reformed several schools and earning her Ph.D. at the University of Maryland. She discusses attending the March on Washington, women in the civil rights movement and the drawbacks of integration.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655591
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (34 pages) (Box-folder 15/178)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 156.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 156.MV.002
  - Vivian Ann Ellis oral history interview conducted by Nikita Glenn, 2005-11-04, AFC 2004/007: 157
    Vivian Ellis was a secretary for the deputy mayor of New York City.
    The interview includes Vivian Ellis' memories of growing up in Wilmington, Delaware, playing several sports and meeting Jesse Owens. She recalls attending business school, moving to New York to pursue her career as a secretary and working for the deputy mayor of New York City. She also discusses discrimination on buses, the civil rights movement and her retirement years in Florida.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655592
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (15 pages) (Box-folder 15/179)
    - Graphic Images, 3 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/457)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 157.MV.001
  - Jeanne Hudgens oral history interview conducted by Joy Thompson, 2003, AFC 2004/007: 158
    Jeanne Hudgens was a teacher and civic leader.
    The interview includes Jeanne Hudgens' memories of growing up in North Carolina, attending North Carolina Central University and Columbia University for her master's degree. She recalls teaching high school, her career at the University of Bridgeport, and working for several organizations related to education and child care. She discusses her work as head of education for the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) and directing the Greensboro, North Carolina Head Start program.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655255
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (31 pages) (Box-folder 15/180)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 158.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 158.MV.002
  - Clay Evans oral history interview conducted by Leon Hendrix, 2006, AFC 2004/007: 159
    Clay Evans was a civil rights activist and the minister of Fellowship Missionary Baptist Church in Chicago, Illinois.
    The interview includes Clay Evans' memories of growing up in Tennessee, the influence of church, and moving to Chicago, Illinois. He recalls founding the Fellowship Missionary Baptist Church, participating in the civil rights movement with Operation Push, and his friendships with Martin Luther King, Jr. and Jesse Jackson. He also discusses his faith and African American leadership.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655594
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (18 pages) (Box-folder 15/181)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 159.MV.001
  - Bernice Fiest oral history interview conducted by DeAndrea Solomon, 2005, AFC 2004/007: 160
    Bernice Fiest was a teacher, librarian and principal.
    The interview includes Bernice Fiest's memories of growing up in Tyler, Texas, attending Texas College and her first job teaching in school in West Texas. She recalls traveling on segregated buses, teaching in Houston, Texas and earning her master's degree at Prairie View A&M College. She discusses desegregation of schools, the elementary school that was named after her, and her involvement at church. A co-worker and student of Fiest's are also interviewed.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655595
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (35 pages) (Box-folder 15/182)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 160.MV.001
  - Henry Foster oral history interview conducted by Kenneth Gilkes, 2005-10-21, AFC 2004/007: 161
    Henry Foster was an obstetrician and gynecologist in Arkansas and Tennessee.
    The interview includes Henry Foster's memories of growing up in Pine Bluff, Arkansas and attending Morehouse College and the University of Arkansas Medical School. He recalls the integration of Little Rock High School, meeting his wife, his career as a doctor and his nomination for U. S. Surgeon General. He also offers advice to young African Americans.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655502
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (37 pages) (Box-folder 15/183)
    - Graphic Images, 6 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/459)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (MiniDV) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DVCAM) (64 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 161.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 161.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 161.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 161.MV.004
  - Norman C. Francis oral history interview conducted by Jeanine M. Price, 2002-10-02, AFC 2004/007: 162
    Norman C. Francis was a lawyer and president of Xavier University.
    The interview includes Norman C. Francis' memories of growing up in Lafayette, Louisiana, attending Xavier University. He recalls becoming the first African American to attend Loyola University Law School and his friendships with Moon Landrieu and other future leaders of New Orleans. He discusses serving in the army during the Korean War, his participation in the civil rights movement as a lawyer, and becoming the first lay president of Xavier University.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655523
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (34 pages) (Box-folder 15/184)
    - Graphic Images, 1 photograph: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/460)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (MiniDV) (300 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 162.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 162.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 162.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 162.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 162.MV.005
  - Lafayette Frederick oral history interview conducted by Terrell Robinson, 2006, AFC 2004/007: 163
    Lafayette Frederick was a professor of biology at Howard University.
    The interview includes Lafayette Frederick's memories of growing up in Missouri and attending Tuskegee Institute, where he studied botany and agriculture. He recalls serving in the navy at the end of World War II, earning his Ph.D. in botany at Washington State University and starting his teaching career at Southern University.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655596
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (42 pages) (Box-folder 16/185)
    - Graphic Images, 8 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/461)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 163.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 163.MV.002
  - Jesse Gooding oral history interview conducted by Jerry Walker, 2005-11-17, AFC 2004/007: 164
    Jesse Gooding was the president of the Dayton, Ohio branch of the NAACP.
    The interview includes Jesse Gooding's memories of growing up in Louisiana, serving in the segregated military and attending Wilberforce University, where he majored in chemistry. He recalls job discrimination and his career at Wright Patterson Air Force Base. He discusses joining the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), protesting job discrimination in Dayton, Ohio and leading the Dayton branch of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP).
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655597
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (24 pages) (Box-folder 16/186)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 164.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 164.MV.002
  - Marcus Gunter oral history interview conducted by Cheri Carter, 2002-09-30, AFC 2004/007: 165
    Marcus Gunter was a music teacher, marching band director and saxophonist.
    The interview includes Marcus Gunter's memories of growing up in Nashville, Tennessee, attending Tuskegee Institute and playing saxophone with the Melody Barons. He recalls performing music while serving in the army during World War II, and teaching music at Pearl High School in Nashville. He discusses directing the Pearl marching band, taking over his family's funeral home business and supporting historically black colleges and universities.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655598
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (27 pages) (Box-folder 16/187)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (MiniDV) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 165.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 165.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 165.MV.003
  - Arnett Bodenhamer oral history interview conducted by Wendell I. Johnson, 2006-11-20, AFC 2004/007: 166
    Arnett Bodenhamer was a businessman and the president of the Nashville, Tennessee branch of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.
    The interview includes Arnett Bodenhamer's memories of growing up in Nashville, Tennessee, and serving in the army during the Korean and Vietnam Wars. He recalls the segregation and discrimination in Nashville, starting his business and joining the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655568
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (64 pages) (Box-folder 16/188)